Jaiaid Mobin

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Summary _

I am a 3rd year (ongoing) Ph.D. student. My research focus is workload optimization for GPU and disaggregated data centers. I am interested in getting opportunities to gain more hands-on experience in DDL deployment and optimization in HPC. As a Ph.D. student I have published a poster in A-tier conferences as the first author, have collaborated on workshop paper and poster, and have done paper and artifact reviews.

Education .

Rochester Institute of Technology

Rochester, NY, USA

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

August, 2022 - Present

 $\bullet \ \ \textbf{Research Topic} - \textit{GPU Computing, Continual Training and Inference System}$

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

Dhaka, Bangladesh

M.Sc. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

August, 2022

Thesis Title — Transit Network Design For Evacuation Modeling Using Heuristic and Multi-Objective Optimization Based Approaches

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

Dhaka, Bangladesh

B.Sc. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

September, 2017

Publications (First Author/Collaborations) ___

Towards Efficient Python Interpreter for Tiered Memory Systems, *Poster*

USENIX Conference on File and Storage Technologies (FAST), 2024

https://par.nsf.gov/biblio/10495018

COLTI: Towards Concurrent and Co-located DNN Training and Inference, Poster (Best Poster Award)

ACM International Symposium on High-Performance Parallel and Distributed Computing (HPDC), 2023

https://www.hpdc.org/2023/program/accepted/

Towards Data Gravity and Compliance Aware Distributed Deep Learning on Hybrid Clouds, Workshop Article

Workshop on Data Fabric for Hybrid Clouds, 2022

https://hipc.org/wdfhc/

Multi-objective optimization and heuristic based solutions for evacuation modeling, Journal Article

Transportation research interdisciplinary perspectives, 2023

https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0245058

 $\textbf{Efficient association mapping from k-mers-an application in finding sex-specific sequences}, \textit{\textit{Journal Article}}$

Plos One, 2021

https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0245058

Reference-free association mapping from sequencing reads using k-mers, Journal Article

Bio-protocol, 2020

https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC7842384/

A heuristic aided Stochastic Beam Search algorithm for solving the transit network design problem, Journal Article

Swarm and Evolutionary Computation, 2019

https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S2210650218302414

Professional Experience _

Graduate Research Assistant, January 2024 - Current, August 2022 - May 2023

Rochester Institute of Technology, Rochester, NY, USA

- Investigate Research Problem
- · Study and review research paper

Graduate Teaching Assistant, August 2023 - December 2023

Rochester Institute of Technology, Rochester, NY, USA

• Answering Student's gueries about homework in office hours or in Discord

Senior Software Engineer, Software Engineer, July 2018 - April 2022

BJIT Ltd - Offshore Software Development Company, House-7, Road-2/C, Block-J, Baridhara, Dhaka

- Act as representative of <5 member team.
- Provide initial system design based on client requirement as a representative of small team
- Train newly recruited Engineers
- · Reviewed client expectations and project parameters and suggested software packages that met requirements.

Professional Project Experience

Device Interfacing Software Improvement

- Contributed to build and solve issues in building a codebase in MSVC2019 which is earlier built using MSVC2012 and clear documentation was not
 available
- Fixed bug in C# codebase and implemented a small feature

Virtual Background Feature Implement

- Used google **Mediapipe sdk** to implement library to remove background, add background, blur background (provided as a static library for Windows)
- Library is developed using C++ (MSVC2017) for 64bit platform, library using Mediapipe SDK is partially built using Bazel build system.
- Resolved some build issues to build mediapipe code using MSVC2017 (Hithub provided version with the necessary feature can be built only by MSVC2019)

Directshow Source Filter Development

- Repurposed code from existing MIT licensed project to create a source filter
- Analyzed requirement of our project and capabilities of Directshow source filter to report what is feasible and accordingly influenced application
 architecture
- Implemented simple IPC mechanism to facilitate communication between COM component and application
- Worked on application backend to interface with custom source filter using C++ (MSVC++14) and C#(.NET 4.7)

Device Control Based on Computer Vision

- Developed Windows application using C++/CLR and VS2015
- Developed simple custom solutions based on computer vision algorithms using OpenCV API to do particular object presence detection for application use case scenario and showed their effectiveness using client provided dataset
- Implemented object detection system in C++ using OpenVINO sdk for Windows10 based application
- Implemented relay control over tcp in C++ using windows networking library and knowledge from the relay documentation

Smartphone User Detection

- Collected Data and trained machine learning model inspired from a given paper in Python3.6 using Numpy, Scikit-Learn package
- Implemented simple communication over Http protocol locally to connect front end code and backend ML inference using Flask, JSON packege

Content Based HTTP/HTTPS Traffic Filtering

- Implemented local cache in C++ using Sqlite library in Windows client PC(Windows10)) application
- User can selectively filter categories of content
- Written simple **Javascript** for browser based control panel of client PC application

Skill Set

Languages Python3, C++, C, Java, Bash, SQL, C#, x86 Assembly(fasm)

ML, CV SDK/Framework OpenCV, Scikit-learn, Keras, PyTorch

DBMSMySQL, SQLite, PostgreSQL**Build system**Make, CMake, Bazel

Cloud Environment GCP

CI/CD Gitlab CI/CD

Hypervisor system VirtualBox, Linux KVM

Container Deployment Docker **Cluster Management Toolkit** xCAT

Mobile Platform SDK Android (https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.bitweaver.morsetorch)

Network Tool Wireshark (monitoring), Packet Tracer (simulation), Postman (API testing)

WebFrameworksLaravel, Codeogniter **H/W Development Platform**Arduino, Raspberry Pl

Achievements and Activities	
ALCF Intro to Al-Driven Science on Supercomputers Digital Badge • Workshop on Al in ALCF	December, 2024
ACM HPDC'23 BEST POSTER AWARD • https://twitter.com/ACM_HPDC/status/1671990446174642177/photo/1	June, 2023
PART OF BRICKHACK 9 BEST HEALTH HACK WINNER TEAM • RIT's premiere collegiate hackathon	February, 2023
• From IPA, Japan	February, 2019

March, 2018

ITEE CERTIFICATION

ITEE Level 2, FE ExamOrganized by IPA, Japan